<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: insight | @navyboys]]></title>
  <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/blog/categories/insight/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-13T19:24:22+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://NavySPACE.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[NavySPACE.net]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[navyboys@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Program or be programmed]]></title>
    <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/blog/program-or-be-programmed/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T19:12:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://NavySPACE.net/blog/program-or-be-programmed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I took an online Ruby on Rails bootcamp named <a href="www.gotealeaf.com">TeaLeaf Academy</a> since last month and restart programming again. When we joined the class, we were introduced to see a video on Youtube named <a href="ttps://www.youtube.com/watch?v=imV3pPIUy1k">Program or be Programmed</a> and say something we think about it. Here is my viewpoint and self-introduce to myself.</p>

<p>By the way, I really enjoy this online course and the way they leads.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have worked for two major Japan-based IT solution providers for over ten years, coding with languages such as Oracle PL/SQL, Visual Basic in previous two years, and then transferred to managerial position as project manager and director of a business division. But I really didn’t want to give up technology because I do believe that information technology will change world dramatically than ever before as the video told us, so I took a PHD program researching on data mining algorithms and its application, and fortunately I will get the degree in a few of months.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the world we called enterprise computing I usually participated in, our job is to work with dozens of (sometimes hundreds of) outsourced developers/designers/testers to build up systems like ERP/MES/CRM for big firms, and the project will spend a long period, months to years. So, in 2006, when I heard Google acquired YouTube.com at a $1.65B which founded by only two developers, I was completely shocked. I realised that the way we used to build up systems must different thoroughly, not only the developing languages, but also something like TDD/BDD, CI, Agile(Scrum/XP), Lean startup, etc., which I known afterward.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Back to the video “Program or Programmed”, I have no idea if everyone in the future should learn programming to avoid “being programmed”, but I do believe guys in enterprise computing field should open eyes to find out what’s happening in another world, both technology and way of thinking &amp; working.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Now, I’m running a consulting firm in Shanghai with several developers, serving small business firms in a non-traditional way, and developing our own products at the same time. I will move to Vancouver this summer and also want to build up a team in North America that can cooperate with guys in China in a REMOTE way, which 37 signals oriented and advocated.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
