<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: github | @navyboys]]></title>
  <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-11T12:08:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://NavySPACE.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[NavySPACE.net]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[navyboys@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Github Account Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://NavySPACE.net/github-setup/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-05T21:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://NavySPACE.net/github-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Account needs to be set up with GitHub credentials so that you can push to your repositories on GitHub. Follow the steps below.</p>

<h2 id="configure-github-email">Configure GitHub email</h2>

<p>Make sure that you are using the e-mail address which you used when setting up your Git account.</p>

<p><code>bash
git config --global user.email 'your@email.com'
</code></p>

<h2 id="configure-full-name">Configure full name</h2>

<p>Again, make sure that this is the full name which you originally used to set up your Git account.</p>

<p><code>bash
git config --global user.name 'Your Name'
</code></p>

<h2 id="generate-keys">Generate Keys</h2>

<p>SSH keys are a way to identify trusted computers, without involving passwords. The steps below will walk you through generating an SSH key and then adding the public key to your GitHub account.</p>

<p>Check the directory listing to see if you have files named either <code>id_rsa.pub</code> or <code>id_dsa.pub</code>. If you don’t have either of those files go to <strong>Configuring a New Key</strong>. Otherwise, you can skip to <strong>Add Your Public Key to GitHub</strong> below.</p>

<p><code>bash
cd ~/.ssh
ls -al
</code></p>

<h2 id="configuring-a-new-key">Configuring a New Key</h2>

<p>To generate a new SSH key, copy and paste the text below, making sure to substitute in your email. The default settings are preferred, so when you’re asked to “enter a file in which to save the key” just press enter to continue.</p>

<p><strong>Gotcha</strong>: The first command (that starts with <code>eval</code>) uses <strong>backticks</strong> to quote the text that follows, not single quotes.</p>

<p><code>bash
eval `ssh-agent -s`
ssh-keygen -t rsa -C "your_email@example.com"
</code>
You should see something like the following:</p>

<p><code>bash
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter file in which to save the key (/home/vagrant/.ssh/id_rsa): [Press enter]
</code></p>

<p>Next, you’ll be asked to enter a passphrase. Leave it blank (just hit enter without typing any other characters), as demonstrated below.</p>

<p><code>bash
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase): [Press enter]
Enter same passphrase again: [Press enter]
</code></p>

<p>Which should give you something like this:</p>

<p><code>bash
Your identification has been saved in /Users/you/.ssh/id_rsa.
Your public key has been saved in /Users/you/.ssh/id_rsa.pub.
The key fingerprint is:
01:0f:f4:3b:ca:85:d6:17:a1:7d:f0:68:9d:f0:a2:db your_email@example.com
</code></p>

<p>Then add your new key to the ssh-agent:</p>

<p><code>bash
ssh-add ~/.ssh/id_rsa
</code></p>

<h2 id="add-your-public-key-to-github">Add Your Public Key to GitHub</h2>

<p>From the terminal, type the following:</p>

<p><code>bash
cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub
</code></p>

<p>This will give you a big block of characters which you should highlight and copy from your Terminal/PuTTy window.</p>

<ol>
  <li>In your browser, visit the <a href="https://github.com/settings/admin">Account Settings</a> screen on GitHub.</li>
  <li>Click on <strong>SSH and GPG Keys</strong> on the left sidebar.</li>
  <li>Click <strong>Add SSH Key</strong></li>
  <li>In the Title field, add a descriptive label for the new key.</li>
  <li>Paste your key into the “Key” field.</li>
  <li>Click <strong>Add key</strong>.</li>
  <li>Confirm the action by entering your GitHub password.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
